<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>Documentation Index</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>This is the top-level entry point of the documentation bundle for the
<strong>Tomcat 4</strong> Servlet/JSP container.  Tomcat 4 implements the
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/">Servlet 2.3</a> and
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/">JavaServer Pages 1.2</a>
specifications from Java Software, and includes many additional features that
make it a useful platform for developing and deploying web applications and
web services.</p>

<p>Select one of the links from the navigation menu (to the left) to drill
down to the more detailed documenation that is available.  Each available
manual is described in more detail below.</p>

</section>


<section name="Getting Started">

<p>The following documents will assist you in downloading and installing
Tomcat 4, and (if you wish to) building a distribution from the source code.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="README.txt"><strong>README.txt</strong></a> - Describes the
    contents and directory structure of a Tomcat 4 binary distribution.</li>
<li><a href="RUNNING.txt"><strong>RUNNING.txt</strong></a> - Documents the
    steps necessary to download, install, start, and stop a Tomcat 4 server.
    </li>
<li><a href="BUILDING.txt"><strong>BUILDING.txt</strong></a> - Details the
    steps necessary to download Tomcat 4 source code (and the other packages
    that it depends on), and build a binary distribution from those sources.
    </li>
</ul>

</section>


<section name="Administrators">

<p>The following documents are aimed at <em>System Administrators</em> who
are responsible for installing, configuring, and operating a Tomcat 4 server.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="config/index.html"><strong>Server Configuration Reference</strong></a>
    - Reference manual that documents all available elements and attributes
      that may be placed into a Tomcat 4 <code>conf/server.xml</code> file.
    </li>
</ul>

</section>


<section name="App Developers">

<p>The following documents are aimed at <em>Application Developers</em> who
are constructing web applications or web services that will run on Tomcat.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="appdev/index.html"><strong>Application Developer's Guide</strong></a>
    - An introduction to the concepts of a <em>web application</em> as defined
    in the <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/download.html">Servlet
    2.3 Specification</a>.  Covers basic organization of your web application
    source tree, the structure of a web application archive, and an
    introduction to the web application deployment descriptor
    (<code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>).</li>
<li><a href="servletapi/index.html"><strong>Servlet/JSP Javadocs</strong></a> -
    The Servlet 2.3 and JSP 1.2 API Javadocs.</li>
</ul>

</section>


<section name="Tomcat Developers">

<p>The following documents are for Java developers who wish to contribute to
the development of Tomcat itself, or to better understand its internal
architecture and operation.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="catalina/docs/api/index.html"><strong>Catalina Javadocs</strong></a>
    - Javadoc API documentation for the <em>Catalina</em> servlet container
    portion of Tomcat 4.</li>
<li><a href="jasper/docs/api/index.html"><strong>Jasper Javadocs</strong></a>
    - Javadoc API documentation for the <em>Jasper</em> JSP container
    portion of Tomcat 4.</li>
</ul>

</section>


</body>
</document>

