<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Apache Tomcat</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Find help">

<p>Apache Tomcat support is provided by the community, for the community, on a
purely volunteer basis. This page has been written to help you find the help you
need whilst making the most efficient use of the resources available. The types
of help are presented in the same order they are typically used.</p>

<p>The first resource to check is the documentation. As well as the Tomcat
documentation (make sure you check the documentation for the version you are
using) you should also check the relevant Servlet and/or JSP version. Much of
Tomcat's behaviour is determined by these specifcations and the information in
them is not typically duplciated in the Tomcat documentation.</p>

<p>The logs which Apache Tomcat generates can be a valuable resource when trying
to diagnose a problem. Please review them. You may want to enable debug output
in your Apache Tomcat configuration so that you have more information to help
diagnose the problem.</p>

<p>It is unusual to find a problem that no-one else has seen. The chances are
that your question has been asked and answered by somebody else. Use your
favourite search engine to try and find it.</p>

<p>Answers to very common questions are documented on the
<a href="/faq/">FAQ</a></p>.

<p>The archives for the user mailing list are a rich source of useful
information. Use the search features provided by one of them. A
<a href="list.html">selection of archives</a> is provided on the mailing list
page.</p>

<p>If you have already subscribed to the
<a href="mailto:tomcat-user@jakarta.apache.org">tomcat-user</a> or
<a href="mailto:tomcat-dev@jakarta.apache.org">tomcat-dev</a> discussion lists
you can ask about the problem on those lists. If you are not subscribed, you
will need to subscribe before you can send your question to either of these
lists. The <a href="list.html">mailing list</a> pages provide further
information on how to use the mailing lists as well as subscription
instructions.</p>

<p>If you think you have found a bug, please following the 
<a href="bugreporting.html">bug reporting</a> steps. Particularly if you are
using an older version of Apache Tomcat, there is a good chance that the
problem has been fixed so it is always worth searching the bug database to
see if ths is the case.</p>

<p>There is also an <a href="irc.html">IRC channel</a> dedicated to Tomcat.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
