<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="marc.saegesser@apropos.com">Marc A. Saegesser</author>
    <title>Jakarta Tomcat</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Jakarta Tomcat">

<p>Tomcat is the servlet container that is used in the official
Reference Implementation for the
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlets">Java Servlet</a> and <a 
href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer Pages</a> technologies.  
The Java Servlet and JavaServer Pages specifications are developed by Sun 
under the <a href="http://java.sun.com/aboutJava/communityprocess/">Java 
Community Process</a>.  </p> 

<p>Tomcat is developed in an open and participatory environment and 
released under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses">Apache 
Software License</a>.  Tomcat is intended to be a collaboration of the 
best-of-breed developers from around the world.  We invite you to 
participate in this open development project.  To learn more about getting 
involved, <a href="/site/getinvolved.html">click here</a>.  </p> 

</section>

<section name="Tomcat Versions">
<p>There are several versions of <strong>Tomcat 3.x</strong> currently
available for download:</p>

<ul>
<li>Version 3.3 is the current production quality release for the Servlet 2.2
and JSP 1.1 specifications.  Tomcat 3.3 is the latest continuation of the
Tomcat 3.x architecture and it is more advanced then 3.2.3, which is the 'old'
production quality release.</li>
<li>Version 3.2.3 is the 'old' production quality release and is now in
maintenance only mode.</li>
<li>Version 3.1.1 is a legacy release.</li>
</ul>

<p>
All Tomcat 3.x releases trace their heritage back to the original Servlet and
JSP implementations that Sun donated to the Apache Software Foundation.  The
3.x versions all implement the <strong>Servlet 2.2</strong> and <strong>JSP
1.1</strong> specifications.
</p>

<p><strong>Tomcat 4.0</strong> implements a new servlet container (called
Catalina) that is based on completely new architecture.  The 4.0 release
implements the <strong>Servlet 2.3</strong> and <strong>JSP 1.2</strong>
specifications.  </p> 

<p>The releases are described in more detail below to help you determine 
which one is right for you.  More details about each release can be found in 
the associated release notes.  </p> 

<p><strong>Tomcat 3.1.x</strong>.  The 3.1 release contained several 
improvements over Tomcat 3.0, including servlet reloading, WAR file 
support and added connectors for the IIS and Netscape web servers.  The 
latest maintenance release, 3.1.1, contained fixes for security problems.  
There is no active development ongoing for Tomcat 3.1.x.  Users of Tomcat 
3.1 should update to 3.1.1 to close the security holes and they are 
strongly encouraged to migrate to the current production release, Tomcat 
3.2.3.</p> 

<p><strong>Tomcat 3.2.x</strong>.  Tomcat 3.2.3 is the current production 
quality release.  Version 3.2 added few new features; the major effort was 
a refactoring of the internals to improve performance and stability.  The 
3.2.1 release, like 3.1.1, was a security patch.  Version 3.2.2 fixed a 
large number of bugs and all known specification compliance issues.  Version
3.2.3 is a security update that closes a serious security hole.  All users
of Tomcat versions prior to 3.2.3 should updgrade as soon as possible.  The 
3.2.x branch will continue in maintenance mode, but no new feature 
releases are planned.</p> 

<p><strong>Tomcat 3.3</strong>.  Tomcat 3.3 continues the refactoring that 
was begun in version 3.2 and carries it to its logical conclusion.  
Version 3.3 provides a much more modular design and allows the servlet 
container to be customized by adding and removing modules that control the 
processing of servlet requests.  This version also contains many 
performance improvements.  Version 3.3 is currently under development and 
has begun beta testing.</p> 

<p><strong>Tomcat 4.0.x</strong>.  Tomcat 4.0.1 is the current production
quality release.  Tomcat 4.0 is the next generation of 
Tomcat.  The 4.0 servlet container (Catalina) has been developed from the 
ground up for flexibility and performance.  Version 4.0 implements the 
final released versions of the Servlet 2.3 and JSP 1.2 specifications.
As required by the specifications, Tomcat 4.0 also supports web applications
built for the Servlet 2.2 and JSP 1.1 specifications with no changes.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>

