<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="marc.saegesser@apropos.com">Marc A. Saegesser</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <title>Apache Tomcat</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Apache Tomcat">

<p>Apache Tomcat is the servlet container that is used in the official
Reference Implementation for the
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlets">Java Servlet</a> and <a 
href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer Pages</a> technologies.  
The Java Servlet and JavaServer Pages specifications are developed by Sun 
under the <a href="http://jcp.org/en/introduction/overview">Java 
Community Process</a>.  </p> 

<p>Apache Tomcat is developed in an open and participatory environment and 
released under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses">Apache 
Software License</a>.  Apache Tomcat is intended to be a collaboration of the 
best-of-breed developers from around the world.  We invite you to 
participate in this open development project.  To learn more about getting 
involved, <a href="/site/getinvolved.html">click here</a>.  </p> 

</section>

<section name="Apache Tomcat Versions">
<p>For the impatient, current Apache Tomcat production quality releases vs.
Servlet/JSP specifications:</p>

<table class="detail-table">

<tr>
  <th><strong>Servlet/JSP Spec</strong></th>
  <th><strong>Apache Tomcat version</strong></th>
</tr>

<tr>
  <td>2.4/2.0</td>
  <td>5.5.9</td>
</tr>

<tr>
  <td>2.3/1.2</td>
  <td>4.1.31</td>
</tr>

<tr>
  <td>2.2/1.1</td>
  <td>3.3.2</td>
</tr>

</table>

<p>To help you determine which release is right for you, the
<a href="whichversion.html">releases are described in more detail</a>.</p> 

<p>Please note that alhough we offer downloads and documentation of older
releases, such as Apache Tomcat 3.x and 4.x, we strongly encourage users to use the
latest stable version of Apache Tomcat whenever possible.  We recognize that upgrading
across major version may not be a trivial task, and some support is still
offered on the mailing list for users of old versions.  However, because of the
community-driven support approach, the older your version the less people would
be interested or able to support you.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
