<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="setup.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <title>Tomcat Setup</title>
  </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Introduction">



  </section>

  <section name="Windows">

    <p>
      Installing Tomcat on Windows can be done easily using the Windows 
      installer. Its interface and functionality is similar to other wizard
      based installers, with only a few items of interest.
    </p>

    <p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Installation as a service</strong>: Tomcat will be 
            installed as a Windows
            NT/2k/XP service no matter what setting is selected. Using the
            checkbox on the component page sets the service as "auto"
            startup, so that Tomcat is automatically startup when Windows
            starts. For optimal security, the service should be affected a
            separate user, with reduced permissions (see the Windows Services
            administration tool and its documentation).</li>
        <li><strong>Java location</strong>: The installer will use the registry
            or the JAVA_HOME environment variable to determine the base path
            of the JDK or a JRE. If only a JRE (or an incorrect path) 
            is specified, Tomcat will run but will be unable to compile
            JSP pages at runtime. Either all webapps will need to be 
            precompiled (this can be easily done using the Tomcat deployer),
            or the <code>lib\tools.jar</code> file from a JDK installation
            to the <code>common\lib</code> path of the Tomcat installation.
            </li>
        <li><strong>Tray icon</strong>: When Tomcat is run as a service, there
            will not be any tray icon present when Tomcat is running. Note that
            when choosing to run Tomcat at the end of installation, the tray
            icon will be used even if Tomcat was installed as a service.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>The installer will create shortcuts allowing starting and configuring 
       Tomcat. It is important to note that Tomcat administration web 
       application can only be used when Tomcat is started.</p>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
