<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="tomcatuser.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="funkman@apache.org">Tim Funk</author>
    <title>About Tomcat User</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Preface">
<p>
    This is about the Tomcat user list.
    <a href="mailto:tomcat-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Subscribe</a>
    and
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">general information</a>
    can be found
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail2.html">here</a>.
    It is a high volume list! For those who can't handle that kind of traffic,
    you can also get it in
    <a href="tomcat-user-digest-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">
        digest form.
    </a>


    If you post to tomcat-user, use good etiquette, ask good questions,
    and use Best Practices, and also please read the docs, faqs, readme,
    and search the archives before asking a question.

    <br/><br/>
    Here are some links about how to use mailing lists and standard etiquette
    in using mailing lists. These links are not Tomcat specific! Please do
    not contact the author of these documents with questions.
    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1855.txt">
          Netiquette Guidelines (RFC 1855)
        </a></li>
      <li>
        <a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">
        How To Ask Questions The Smart Way
        </a>
      </li>
    </ul>

</p>
</section>


<section name="Questions">
  <ul>

     <li>
       <a href="#why">
         Why won't people answer my question?
       </a>
     </li>

     <li>
       <a href="#unsubscribe">
         How do I unsubscribe?
        </a>
      </li>



      <li>
       <a href="#wheretopost">
         Should I post to tomcat-user or tomcat-dev?
        </a>
      </li>

<!--
     <li>
       <a href="#connectors">
         Why isn't there a connector's list?
        </a>
      </li>

     <li>
       <a href="#newsgroup">
         Why isn't there a newgroup/bridge?
        </a>
      </li>
-->

  </ul>
</section>


<section name="Answers">

    <question>
      <a name="why">
               Why won't people answer my question?
      </a>
    </question>
    <answer>
        It could be one of any of the following answers:
         <ul>
            <li>No one knows the answer.</li>
            <li>Everyone is ignoring you.</li>
            <li>The person  who knows the answer hasn't gotten around to
                it yet.</li>
             <li>The person  who knows the answer hasn't gotten around to
                it yet. (So please don't post the same question
                    multiple times)</li>
          </ul>

         In other words - you get what you pay for. If you phrase
         you question intelligently and not make your question annoying,
         your quality of support will
         probably better than any commercial help support.
         <br/><br/>

         In particular, some readers on the tomcat-user list have been
         known to automatically ignore
         a message which meets any of the following criteria:
            (You have been warned)
         <ul>
            <li> "help" in the subject line
                (we know you need help by writing in the first place)</li>
            <li> plz or please in the subject line.
                We already know you need help.</li>
            <li> ALL CAPS IN THE SUBJECT LINE. (Sorry for anyone
                emailing from a mainframe)</li>
            <li> Do not place !! (more than 2!) in the subject line.
                 The number of exclamation points has no relation to anyone's
                 interest in answering the question. In fact - it has a higher
                 chance at being ignored.
            </li>
            <li> Your e-mail has a return receipt. You don't need to know
                I got the message.</li>
            <li> Select posters who have consistently displayed no
                desire to research before posting a question.
            </li>
         </ul>
  </answer>


  <question>
      <a name="unsubscribe">
         How do I unsubscribe?
      </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
      <ul>
        <li>To unsubscribe, e-mail:
            tomcat-user-unsubscribe@jakarta.apache.org</li>
        <li>For additional commands, e-mail:
            tomcat-user-help@jakarta.apache.org</li>
      </ul>
      If you are unable to unsubscribe, it could be due to your e-mail system
      mangling your e-mail address or you have subscribed under an alias.
      In that case, maybe
      <a href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=tomcat-user&amp;m=104190907020995&amp;w=2">
         this thread
      </a> will help.

      <br/><br/>
      If you send an e-mail to the moderator to remove you from the list,
      be prepared to continue receiving more e-mails from the lists until
      the moderator has an opportunity to remove you from the list.
  </answer>


  <question>
      <a name="wheretopost">
         Should I post to tomcat-user or tomcat-dev?
      </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    tomcat-user is for user based questions for tomcat. That means anyone who is
    developing any type of software to be used with tomcat.
    <br/><br/>

    tomcat-dev is the forum to discuss changes to the Tomcat's source code. If your question
    is not related to changing the source code as maintained by the tomcat committers,
    then it does not belong here, it belongs in tomcat-user.

    <br/><br/>

    If you wish to extend tomcat using your own Valve, Realm, or anything else ... those
    discussions belong in tomcat-user. You might be using Tomcat's internal API but unless
    your changes are going back into the official source tree, the question belongs
    in tomcat-user.

  </answer>

</section>


</body>
</document>
