<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="bugs.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="funkman@apache.org">Tim Funk</author>
    <title>Bugs</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Preface">
If you think you found a bug,
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/bugreport.html">read this page</a>.

</section>

<section name="Questions">
<p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#gotone">I have a bug, what do I do?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#feature">Why does feature ABC work
        in Servlet Container XYZ but not in Tomcat?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ignored">I submitted a bug, why is it ignored?</a></li>
  </ul>
</p>
</section>


<section name="Answers">

    <question>
        <a name="gotone">I have a bug, what do I do?</a>
    </question>
    <answer>
    Unless you have the source code reference in Tomcat which is wrong,
    it may not be a bug. E-mail the
    <a href="tomcatuser.html">user list</a> and confirm its a bug. Also
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/bugreport.html">
    read this first</a> from the tomcat site about reporting a bug.
    </answer>

    <question>
       <a name="feature">Why does feature ABC work in Servlet
         Container XYZ but not in Tomcat?
       </a>
    </question>

    <answer>
    There could be a good chance that the other servlet container could
    be implementing the spec wrong.
    </answer>

    <question>
      <a name="ignored">
        I submitted a bug, why is it ignored?
      </a>
    </question>

    <answer>
    Any of the following may affect someone acting on a bug:
    <ul>
      <li>
        Is it a bug?
      </li>
      <li>
        Is your description good?
      </li>
      <li>
        Is your description complete?
      </li>
      <li>
        Can a developer <b>easily</b> reproduce the bug in their own environment?
      </li>
      <li>
        Have you provided a patch? Is it against cvs? Using the correct file? Using
        <code>cvs diff -u</code>
      </li>
      <li>
        Is your patch coded well?
      </li>
      <li>
        Is your solution "good"?
      </li>
    </ul>

    Some developers are uncomfortable submitting patches to code they are
    unfamiliar with. The committers are not experts in all areas of Tomcat.
    It may be that the developer who has the ability to adequately review
    the patch may be too busy or unable to review the bug. That is the bad news,
    the good news is Tomcat is Open Source and you can build and use your own
    release until the fix gets back into the official release.
    </answer>

</section>

</body>
</document>
