<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="connectors.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="funkman@apache.org">Tim Funk</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <title>Connectors</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Preface">
  <p>
    Please see the
    <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/wiki/apachewiki.cgi?Tomcat/Links">
        Other Resources
    </a> Link for other pages describing how they were able to link
    Tomcat with a connector. With luck, someone documented their experience
    in an environment which is similar to yours.

</p>
</section>


<section name="Questions">
<p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="#jk">
        What is JK (or AJP)?
      </a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="#vs">
        Which connector: mod_jserv, JK, JK2, mod_webapp or mod_proxy?
      </a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="#integrate">
        Why should  I integrate Apache  with Tomcat? (or not)
      </a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="#boot">
        At boot, is order of start up (Apache vs Tomcat) important?
      </a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="#jkloc">
     JK2 doesn't seem to be using my settings in my
     <code>workers2.properties</code> file
     such as creating the shm file or mapping the URIs listed to Tomcat,
     what's wrong?
      </a>
    </li>

    <li>
      <a href="#generated">
      Is there any way to control the content of automatically generated
      <code>mod_jk.conf-auto</code>? I need my own specific commands added to it.
      </a>
    </li>


    <li>
      <a href="#bind">
      How do I bind to a specific ip address?
      </a>
    </li>

    <li>
      <a href="#binary">
      Where is the binary distribution of my connector?
      </a>
    </li>

  </ul>
</p>
</section>


<section name="Answers">

  <question>
    <a name="jk">What is JK (or AJP)?</a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    AJP is a wire protocol. It an optimized version of the HTTP protocol to
    allow a standalone web server such as Apache talk to Tomcat. Historically,
    Apache has always been much faster than Tomcat at serving static content.
    The idea is to let Apache serve the static content when possible, then
    proxy the request back to Tomcat for Tomcat related content.
  </answer>

  <question>
    <a name="vs">
      Which connector: mod_jserv, JK, JK2, mod_webapp or mod_proxy?
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Stay away from mod_webapp, aka warp. It is deprecated and unsupported
        due to lack of developer interest and there are better options such
        as jk and jk2. It WILL NOT run on windows.
      </li>
      <li>
        mod_jserv at this point is unsupported and will not be supported
        in Tomcat 5. mod_jserv was the original connector which supported
        the ajp protocol.
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>mod_jk is great and should be used for production. It is getting
        fixes as needed (which is now rare). </b>
      </li>
      <li>
        jk2 is a refactoring of mod_jk and uses the Apache Portable
        Runtime (apr). If you are using Apache 2.0,
        you'll might want to use jk2. But this may not be production
        worthy for everyone. (YMMV) jk2 has quirks which may not be acceptable
        to all.
      </li>
      <li>mod_proxy. A cheap way to proxy without the hassles of configuring JK.
        This solution lacks sticky session load balancing. If you don't
        need some of the features of jk, jk2 - this is a very simple
        alternative.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </answer>

   <question>
     <a name="integrate">
        Why should  I integrate Apache  with Tomcat? (or not)
     </a>
   </question>
   <answer>
    There are many reasons to integrate Tomcat with Apache. And there are
    reasons why it
    should not be done too. Needless to say, everyone will disagree with
    the opinions here.
    With the upcoming performance of Tomcat 5, performance reasons
    become harder to justify. So here are the issues to discuss in
    integrating vs not.
   <br/><br/>

  <ul>
    <li>
      Clustering. By using Apache as a front end you can let Apache act as a
      front door to your content to multiple Tomcat instances. If one of your
      Tomcats fails, Apache
      ignores it and your Sysadmin can sleep through the night. This point
      could be ignored if you use a hardware loadbalancer and Tomcat's
      clustering capabilities.
    </li>
    <li>
      Clustering/Security. You can also use Apache as a front door to different
      Tomcats for
      different URL namespaces (/app1/, /app2/, /app3/, or virtual hosts).
      The Tomcats can then be each in a protected area
      and from a security point of view, you only need to worry about the
      Apache server. Essentially, Apache becomes a smart proxy server.
    </li>
    <li>
       Security. This topic can sway one either way. Java has the security
       manager while Apache has a larger mindshare and more tricks with
       respect to security. I won't go into this
       in more detail, but let Google be your friend. Depending on your scenario,
       one might be better than the other. But also keep in mind, if you run
       Apache with
       Tomcat - you have two systems to defend, not one.
    </li>
    <li>
       Add-ons. Adding on CGI, perl, PHP is very natural to Apache. Its
       slower and more
       of a kludge for Tomcat. Apache also has hundreds of modules that can
       be plugged in
       at will. Tomcat can have this ability, but the code hasn't been
       written yet.
    </li>
    <li>
       Decorators! With Apache in front of Tomcat, you can perform any number
       of decorators that
       Tomcat doesn't support or doesn't have the immediate code support.
       For example,
       mod_headers, mod_rewrite, and mod_alias could be written for Tomcat,
       but why reinvent the wheel when Apache has done it so well?
    </li>
    <li>
      Speed. Apache is faster at serving static content than Tomcat. But unless
      you have a high traffic site, this point is useless. But in some scenarios,
      tomcat can be faster than apache. So benchmark YOUR site.
    </li>
    <li>
       Socket handling/system stability. Apache has better socket handling
       with respect
       to error conditions than Tomcat. The main reason is Tomcat must perform
       all its socket handling via the JVM which needs to be cross platform.
       The problem
       is socket optimization is a platform specific ordeal. Most of the
       time the java
       code is fine, but when you are also bombarded with dropped connections,
       invalid
       packets, invalid requests from invalid IP's, Apache does a better job
       at dropping these error conditions than JVM based program. (YMMV)
    </li>
    <li>
    <a href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=tomcat-user&amp;m=104874913017036&amp;w=2">Here </a>
    is a great response from Craig R. McClanahan. If you have free time,
    read emails by him in any of the list archives. You'll learn a lot.
    </li>
    </ul>
  </answer>

  <question>
    <a name="boot">
      At boot, is order of start up (Apache vs Tomcat) important?
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    No. This way - either apache or tomcat can be restarted at any time
    independent of one another.
  </answer>

  <question>
    <a name="jkloc">
     JK2 doesn't seem to be using my settings in my
     <code>workers2.properties</code> file
     such as creating the shm file or mapping the URIs listed to Tomcat,
     what's wrong?
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    JK2 is not finding your <code>workers2.properties</code> file.
    Specify it's location in your <code>httpd.conf</code> file by adding:

    <br /><br />
    <code>
        JkSet config.file /full/system/path/to/workers2.properties
    </code>
    <br /><br />
    <a href='http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?t=105784893200003&amp;r=1&amp;w=2'>
        Thread which spawned this question.
    </a>
  </answer>


  <question>
    <a name="generated">
    Is there any way to control the content of automatically generated
    <code>mod_jk.conf-auto</code>? I need my own specific commands added
    to it.
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    There really is no need to. Just copy the automatically generated
    <code>mod_jk.conf-auto</code> and edit it manually to your preference.
    None of production tomcat installations really use <code>mod_jk.conf-auto</code>
    as it is.
  </answer>

  <question>
    <a name="bind">
    How do I bind to a specific ip address?
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    Each Connector element allows an <tt>address</tt> property. For example:
<source>
&lt;Connector className="org.apache.coyote.tomcat4.CoyoteConnector"
           address="192.168.1.1"
           port="8080" minProcessors="5" maxProcessors="75"
           enableLookups="true" redirectPort="8443"
           acceptCount="100" debug="0" connectionTimeout="20000"
           useURIValidationHack="false" disableUploadTimeout="true" /&gt;
</source>

    For a more complete description of the Connector config,
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/config/http.html">see the
    HTTP Connector docs</a>
    or the
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/config/http.html">see the
    AJP Connector docs</a>.


  </answer>

  <question>
    <a name="binary">
    Where can I download a binary distribution of my connector?
    </a>
  </question>
  <answer>
    You can't: you need to download the source and compile it
    for your platform.  The source distributions are available
    from the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/sourceindex.cgi">standard location.</a>
    Note that JPackage.org has RPM distributions for the connectors
    as well as tomcat itself: <a href="http://www.jpackage.org">JPackage.org</a>
  </answer>


</section>


</body>
</document>
